Leah: To understand what coding is all
about and how it works, you first have to
know how a computer system processes data.
To do this we will start by
looking at a central processing
unit or CPU and what it does.
Jack: CPUs are silicon chips
found in almost all devices from
smartwatches to computers and
act as the brain of the device.
The CPU also called the main processor is
the part of the device that is responsible
for processing and executing instructions.
The CPU is the core component that
defines a computer but can only
function alongside other hardware.
This silicon chip sits in a
socket on a main circuit board or
mother board inside the device.
It is connected to all other aspects
of the hardware, and integrates
the various signals and processes
to produce the overall function.
Leah: CPUs consist of billions of
microscopic transistors which allow it to
make calculations needed to run programs
that are stored on a system's memory.
These transistors are like little
switches that turn on and off conveying
the '1's and '0's that translate into
everything that is done on a computer
from watching videos to writing an email.
This system of ‘1’s and ‘0’s is referred
to as binary, meaning that there are two
possible states: on [‘1’] and off [‘0’].
Circuits consisting of binary inputs
controlled by transistors, form the
basis of all commercially available
contemporary computational devices.
Jack: CPUs take instructions
from a program or application
and perform a calculation.
This process is in 3 stages, it
'fetches' the instruction from the
RAM, 'decodes' it and 'executes' it.
The executed instruction or calculation
can involve basic arithmetic, comparing
numbers, performing a function, or
moving numbers around in memory.
Leah: In modern systems the CPU feeds data
to specialised hardware as it is required.
The main component of CPU chips
are the processing units, which
are referred to as ‘cores’.
Originally CPU's had single
processing cores but modern ones
have multiple cores allowing multiple
instructions to be given at once.
Jack: Most modern CPUs have 2 or
4 cores, 6 are mainstream and more
expensive chips can have from 8 up to 64.
Clock speed measured in gigahertz,
denotes how many instructions a CPU
can handle per second and a faster
clock speed means a faster processor.